Guide to the John Hart Ely Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Hart Ely papers
1833-2003
MS 1976
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
19.25
(32 boxes)
The John Hart Ely papers consists of teaching files, research papers, drafts of articles, legal briefs, professional and personal correspondence, and video tapes documenting Ely's legal and teaching career. The bulk of the collection contains accumulated notes and research materials pertaining to Ely's writings on constitutional law from 1968 to 2003.
Ely, John Hart, 1938-
Biographical / Historical
John Hart Ely was born in New York City on December 3, 1938. He received his A.B. from Princeton University in 1960 and LL.B. from Yale Law School in 1963. He held the following academic appointments: professor, Yale Law School, 1968-1973; professor, Harvard Law School, 1973-1982; professor, Stanford Law School, 1982-1996, dean of the Stanford Law school from 1982-1987; and professor, University of Miami School of Law, 1996-2003.
In 1962 he clerked for Abe Fortas and assisted with drafting a brief on behalf of Clarence Gideon who had been tried and convicted without legal representation. The next year, Gideon v. Wainwright was overturned by the United States Supreme Court on the grounds that underprivileged citizens accused of serious crimes are entitled to legal representation paid for by the government. After graduating from Yale Law School, he served as the youngest member of the Warren Commission that investigated the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. He also was a criminal defense lawyer in San Diego. In 1975 he left academia briefly to work for the U. S. Department of Transportation serving as legal counsel to Secretary William Coleman; Ely was involved in litigation relating to landing rights in the United States for the Concorde, the supersonic transport.
Ely's most important work was in constitutional law and he was best known for his book, Democracy and Distrust: A Theory of Judicial Review (Harvard, 1980). His other books include War and Responsibility (Princeton, 1993) and On Constitutional Ground (Princeton, 1996).
Ely died on October 25, 2003, in Miami, Florida.
Conditions Governing Access
The computer files in Accession 2012-M-023 are closed until processed. All other materals are open to research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Scope and Contents
The John Hart Ely papers consists of teaching files, research papers, drafts of articles, legal briefs, professional and personal correspondence, and video tapes documenting Ely's legal and teaching career. The bulk of the collection contains accumulated notes and research materials pertaining to Ely's writings on constitutional law from 1968 to 2003.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert D. Ely, 2010-2011.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by topic and additional material.
Concorde (Jet transports); Constitutional law -- United States; Judicial review -- United States; Law -- Study and teaching -- United States; War and emergency powers -- United States -- History; Coleman, William T. (William Thaddeus), 1920-2017; Ely, John Hart, 1938-; Fortas, Abe, 1910-1982; United States. Department of Transportation; Harvard Law School; Stanford University. School of Law; University of Miami. School of Law; Yale Law School
- Inventory, 1833-2003
  - Course books
    - Advanced constitutional law, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Gerrymanders, Stanford University, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - War and the constitution, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - War powers litigation seminar, University of Miami Law School, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Underwater treasure, Stanford University, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Admiralty Cases and Material, Second Edition, Part I, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - The Law and Democracy, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Constitutional theory seminar, Harvard Law School, 1982 spring (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Foreign Relations and National Security Law, Part I, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Conflict of Laws, 5th Edition, Part I, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Criminal Law and Procedure, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Comparative constitutional law, University of Miami Law School, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Constitutional law, 1979 summer (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - National Security Law, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Teaching and law school documents
    - Constitutional law, Aspen, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Election law, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
    - The Law and Democracy, Part I, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Law schools
      - Recommendations, 1993-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Law school rankings, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Legal education
      - Speakers, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
      - Tamar Frankel vita, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Georgetown, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Stanford Law School course roster, 1996 spring (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Boston College Paris proposal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Lectures invited to give, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Dray, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - East Palo Alto clinic, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Foley, Hoag, & Eliot, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Ackerman, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Teaching, Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Association of American Law Schools (AALS) Special Committee on Placement, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Writing projects for students, etc., Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Clinical teaching ("everyone should do it"), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Yale Law School
        - National security litigation: reports of the Bosnia team, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Civil complaint vs. President Clinton re: Bosnian independence, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO): legal authorization of United States military force, notes and research, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 25)
        - Tom Campbell's 1998 Bosnia resolution (Box 3, Folder 26)
        - Campbell v. Clinton, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Law School course files and research
    - Teaching materials
      - Constitutional law: teaching materials, Circa 2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Spring 2000 exam [explanation of answers] (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Top Tens (Constitutional law I), Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Exam questions, constitutional law, 1987-2002 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - U.S. Constitutional Law II-A supplementary materials, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Assignment: Lochner, 2002 March 5 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - University of Miami Law School Constitutional Law II exam, 2002 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Recommendations: former students, etc., 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Teaching technique, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Non-constitutional law exams, 1977-1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Teaching materials, unpublished (by others), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - University of Virginia School of Law independent study paper on Roe (Liz Magill), 1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Courses (done)
      - Constitution and the Electoral Process, 2002 fall (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Constitutional Law II, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Art Law, 2001 spring (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Courses taught, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Admiralty, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Conflicts notes, Stanford Law School, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Constitutional Law I, Miami, 1995 spring (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Constitutional Law II
        - 2001 (Box 4, Folder 20)
        - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 21)
        - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Election, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Independent study, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Judicial enforcement of immoral laws, Circa 1999 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - John F. Kennedy seminar, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Final exam questions and answers, National Security Law, 1991 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - National Security Litigation seminar, Yale Law School, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Slavery, etc. course, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Underwater treasure, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Bibliographic analysis, Circa 1985-circa 2000
      - T (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - V (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - W (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Z (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Professor John Hart Ely, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Gerrymandering
      - Texas, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - North Carolina, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Georgia, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Facts bearing on gerrymanders, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Edited drafts of Stanford Law Review (SLR) article on gerrymandering, Circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Random districting programs, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Transparencies, Circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Proportional representation (P.R.), 1997 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Influence district study, Circa 1997 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Influence districts, Circa 1995 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Gerrymanders: notes on articles, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Re-election of incumbents (after districts invalidated), 1996 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Campaign finance
      - Laws, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Legislation, 1983-2002 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Capital punishment news clipping, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Chadha
      - Notes and drafts, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Chadha Project, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Child custody (taking children away), 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Citation studies, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Clinton, Bill, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Cocaine: federal sentencing guideline case study, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Concorde: talk, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Conflicts, decline of, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Congress
      - General, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - As clowns (not dodgers, clowns), 1983-1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - Hiding from decision (includes errand boy/ombudsman stuff), 1988-1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Ducking / president over-reaching, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - Congressional committees, 1990-1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Cooper v. Aaron, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Criminal defense work, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Talks about Democracy and Distrust and related subjects, 1981-2000 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - De facto / de jure, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Dostoyevsky and McCullers, Circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Dostoyevsky / McCullers, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - "Draft" article: reinstituting the draft, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Professional journals, comparative numbers (more law reviews), 1995 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Piece on judicial behavior in immoral regimes, Undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Dred Scott, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Eisenhower, Circa 1997 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Emporia and Scotland Neck (motive and S.C.s), Undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Environment, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Ethnicity, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Foreign policy: policy, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Gerrymanders, 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Habermas and Ely, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Hate crimes, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Housing segregation and voting districts, Circa 1997 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Hume, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Humor, 1969-1998 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Impeachment, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Noncriminal incarceration, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Inheritance taxes, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Initiatives and referenda, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Isolationism, Undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Criticism of "not talking regarding: judicial review, instead regarding: constitution", Undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Paula Jones v. Clinton, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - "Power to the Voters", 2000 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Talks regarding: judicial review, Undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - RFK (Robert F. Kennedy), 2000 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - King, Martin Luther, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Legitimacy, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Lying by government officials (including regarding: wars), 1990 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Magill, Circa 2000 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Agendas of Appointments Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Committees, 1982-1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Common Cause, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Early American conflicts doctrine, Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Fight regarding: consent of instructor racial selection, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Conservatives, silencing of, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Constitutional theory seminar (Stanford Law School), 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Constitutional and international law (Franck and Glennon), spring 1989, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Cooper, Edward, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Critical legal studies, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Constitution and economic (business) interests [talk], 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Daniels, Ernie, 1982-1989 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Dreyfus California Tax Exempt Bond Fund, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Facial neutrality, requirement of - not easily avoidable (answer to Parker's point), Undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Federal courts, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Federalism (values of, if any), 1981 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Fifth Amendment, 1965-1986 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Financing legal education, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Harvard Law School (HLS), 1980-1984 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - International law, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Hiss, Alger, Undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - History Book Club, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Holmes Devise job, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Hoover activities questionnaire, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Hoover Institute, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Inheritance, 1971-1984 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - International law, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Insanity, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Johnson v. Board of Education (panel), 1983 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - LSC curriculum, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Lectures, etc. invited to give, 1984-1990 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Legal malpractice, Undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Liberty, equality, and subjectivity, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - K. MacKinnon, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - McFarland funding of East Palo Alto Community Project (EPA), 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Matsuda, 1989-1991 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Ken and Harle Montgomery, May 27, 1983, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - National security litigation: seminar, Georgetown, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - New York Law School, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Outside evaluations, need for, Undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Miranda piece follow-up, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Drafts: War Powers Resolution piece (Columbia), Undated (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Drafts of "VN" [Viet Nam] pieces (Vietnam), Undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Virginia Law Review and Yale Law Journal: mechanics and draft, 1987-1991 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Reactions to Column ( Columbia Law Review ) piece, 1988-1991 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - "Ely Bill", 1989 (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Feedback on VN-1 and VN-2, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Reactions to Los Angeles Times piece (Kuwait), 1990 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Virginia article followup, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - W & R [ War and Responsibility ]: additional stuff, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Hill - Thomas piece, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Herald piece (teams and trials), 1997 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Harvard Law Review (HLR) Standing piece, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Inquisitorial systems, principally French, 1960-1983 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Reprints, SLR, Gerrymanders, Undated (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Roe, should it be overturned? (Stanford LS correspondence), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Issacharoff and Karlan, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - "Parties Play Voting Rights Role Reversal", 2001 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - More regarding: Bandemer and "political gerrymandering" as a defense, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - On Constitutional Ground reviews, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Brown and Loving, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Monica Lewinsky research articles and correspondence, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Monica - full version, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Mixed government, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - "Brown" opinion book (Balkin), 2000 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - "Ely's Wager" - article research and correspondence, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Elder law titles: research, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 67-69)
    - Agriculture exclusion, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - American Indian legal problems, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Rose Bird campaign, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - American Law Institute (ALI), 1988 (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Black Panther trial, New Haven, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Appointments Committee, 1990-1991 (Box 6, Folder 75-76)
    - Austin, Regina, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - Brilmayer, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Burger court (speeches), 1971, undated (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Carter, Barry, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Center for National Security Studies, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - CHIC - Kent grades, Undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Child beating, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Bush v. Gore: J. H. Ely reviews of articles and research materials with notes, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Election 2000, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Fisher (Kansas Press), 2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Grading curves (University of Miami), 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Health law, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Pardons, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Second course (descriptions), Circa 2001 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Seminar: Initiatives and Referenda, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Stanford memos and lists (current), 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Letters regarding: Stanford, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Stanford Law Journal, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Teaching methods, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Constitutional law
      - Exams, 1968-2001 (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Model answers, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Con Law II, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - University of Miami
      - Law Review committee, 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Law School - current memos and information, 1997-2003 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Overbreadth, Undated (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Panama City, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - "Brad Perry", 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Placement
      - General, Circa 1981-1984 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - Discrimination charges, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Pre-solicitation letter(s), 1982-1986 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Prince Building
      - Money invested (basis), 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Sale and after, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Taxes (real estate), 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - Transfer documents, etc./mortgage, 1979-1982 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Political analysis and philosophy, 1964-1984 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Memos on new "political correctness" of SLS, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Public interest law firm (PILF), 1991-1993 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Public interest placement, 1983-1989 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - University of Puerto Rico, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Race relations, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Random choice, Undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Rawls, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Reaccreditation report (Stanford Law School), 1987 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - Reagan Library, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Reasonable doubt, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Rehnquist, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Separation of powers, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Sidak, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Social Security, 1988-1991 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Speeches as SLS dean (record), 1982-1987 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - "Roadblocks and the Law of Arrest", 1962 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - State of school speeches, 1982-1986 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Students, SLS
      - Characters of, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 46)
      - Speech to incoming, 1982-1986 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Time capsule (misc.), 1980-1988 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Transportation (rail), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Trial advocacy, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Visa (Chase): Budget Rent-a-Car theft, 1990-1991 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - War and Constitution
      - Changes to materials (and notes for teaching), 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 52)
      - Class notes, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Warren, 1963-1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Comments on Weisberg ("Discretion"), Undated (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Weiss, Jonny, 1981, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - White, Byron, 1979-1985 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Yeats Project, 1983-1987 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Michelman correspondence, University of Miami, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Margarine: research and legal opinions, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Military tribunals (taking juries in questionable cases), 2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Mines (land) and war powers, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Mootness (capable of repetition), Circa 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Why not live your morals?, 1981, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Motivation, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Litigation techniques, lectures, 1969-1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Parties, political, 1998-2001 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Perry's new book, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Plane crashes, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Plebiscites, 1970-2002 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Plyler piece, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Confusion of policy analysis with constitutional analysis (both ways) and legal and moral questions, Undated (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Pragmatism, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Presidents, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Press, freedom of, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Public defender elections, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Reagan court op-ed piece, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - "Correct that resumé" (Bosnia), 1994 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Revenge as "justice", 1979-2000 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Second Amendment, 1968-2000 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - "Second edition" notes ( Democracy and Distrust ), 1980-1992 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Rosen, Jeff, response to, Undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Round, Tom (representation-reinforcement), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - "Scalia" piece, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Shaming punishments: research papers, 1990-1998 (Box 8, Folder 27-29)
    - Shaming, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Shapiro piece, 1984-2000 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Soldier of Fortune Magazine court cases, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Taller candidate wins, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Research background files
    - Abortion and crime article research, 1975-2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Affirmative action, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Airline security, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Amendments, constitutional, unratified, Circa 1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Amish, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Animal rights, 2002 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Arms dealing, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Arms trade, international, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Ashcroft (etc.) locking people up post-9/11, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Assassination ban, 1981, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
    - Blackmail conundrum, Circa 1997 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Boerne and Flores (XIV s5 and religion), 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Bowers piece, 1988-1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Bush v. Gore, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Cambodia
      - Secret bombing, 1969-1973 (Box 9, Folder 16)